Guide to the Vice President and Secretary Administrative Records 1925-1965 RG 4.0.1
New York University Libraries, Publisher
Records1925-1965
RG 4.0.1
19 linear feet
New York University
New York University. Office of Vice President and Secretary.
The primary function of the Secretary was to assist the Chancellor in the discharge of his duties. The Secretary conducted correspondence relating to the University, and prepared and maintained the University Council's minutes, documentary materials, records, and correspondence. In addition, the Secretary oversaw faculty personnel records, and supervised the publication of annual reports. These records were mainly accumulated by the Vice President and Secretary's Office during the tenure of Harold Voorhis(1925-1945).
Provenance
The records of the Office of Vice President and Secretary during the Voorhis administration were transferred from the Secretary's Office to the New York University Archives in March 1975 by Dr. E. Frederic Knauth. They were previously stored in Vanderbilt Hall, 40 Washington Square South, where the offices of central administration were located before moving to the Elmer Holmes Bobst Library in 1973. The records consist primarily of administrative correspondence and subject files from the Secretary's office, 1925-1963, with the bulk of the files created during the 1940s and 1950s. They were processed during the academic year 1982/83 by several students of the Archival Training Program at NYU, including: Emery E. Adoradio, Susan Meier, John P. Sokolowski, Gloria J. Walters, and T. Michael Womack. The final arrangement of the records and the construction of this Inventory, based upon preliminary work of the Archives Program students, was performed during the Summer of 1985 by Angela Chin and Elizabeth Liu of the University Archives staff.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Office of Vice President and Secretary was first created as the Office of the Secretary of the University in 1925. The Secretary was appointed by the Council, upon recommendation of the Chancellor, and served as the general executive assistant to the Chancellor. The Office of Secretary became central to the administration of New York University.
The primary function of the Secretary was to assist the Chancellor in the discharge of his duties. The responsibilities delineated in 1925 included: conducting correspondence with individuals and institutions relating to the University at large; coordinating the work of secretaries of the several schools and divisions; preparing and maintaining minutes, documentary materials, records, and conducting correspondence of the Council and its committees. The Secretary affixed the University seal, issued diplomas, certificates and maintained records of these. He maintained personnel records of the faculty, published the University bibliography, supervised the publication of annual reports, and performed other administrative duties assigned by the Chancellor.
The responsibilities of the Secretary increased in volume as the University grew and diversified. In recognition of the importance of the Secretary, the administrative title of the office was changed on July 1, 1945 to Vice Chancellor and Secretary in accordance with the duties assigned to the office by Chancellor Harry Woodburn Chase and the University Council. The title was changed again in 1955 to Vice President and Secretary as a result of a general administrative reorganization under President Henry T. Heald. Several assistant positions to the Secretary were created in 1956. The responsibilities of the Secretary increased in volume and complexity as the University grew and diversified.
Part of the collection deals with the New York University and its activities during the Korean conflict. New York University fell into line with war preparations and strove to define its wartime needs through groups like the American Council on Education, the Department of Higher Education, the Association of American Colleges, the National Education Association, and the Association of American Universities. When the Korean conflict began, colleges and universities around the country joined forces to protect themselves, their students, and their faculty from being overwhelmed by the military effort. During World War II, educational institutions had suffered from a decline in students. Chancellor Chase at New York University wrote in his report of the 1949-50 school year, that "clearly the most careful planning is imperative if we are to maintain our institutional stability. Declining registration means decreased revenue, and lower revenue presents a serious threat to the scope and quality of our services." In accordance with the Selective Service Act of 1948, young men were drafted into the various branches as needed. The universities wanted limitations and guidelines to be set whereby students and faculty could be deferred from service when it was shown that they would better serve their country by remaining in the field of education. On March 31, 1951 a student deferment policy was finally, formally put into effect. Students were able to be deferred if they scored high on a nationally administered scholastic aptitude test, or if they were ranked in the upper part of their class. Universities were also able to request deferments for faculty members. To do so, it was necessary to prove that the individual was of sufficient importance to the University to warrant a deferment. New York University made requests on behalf of some of their faculty. They did so by writing out requests to the local selective service boards.
The military's dilemma over how manpower should be supplied was dealt with in part by expanding their Reserve Officers Training Corps (ROTC) at colleges around the nation. A ROTC program had first been established at the University Heights campus of NYU in 1919. In the 1951-52 school year, for the first time, the Air Force branch of ROTC offered a program at the Washington Square campus of NYU. The quota for the first year of basic training was 1,100 men.
Civilian institutions provided may services during war times. In a letter found in the collection to Frederick W. Nichol, from the NYU chancellor, dated December 21, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 7) the position that NYU had during previous wars was outlined. NYU was responsible for providing training for men in uniform in many fields. They also trained both men and women for jobs in the war industry. In addition, NYU was involved with a variety of government contracts. In 1949, NYU filled out a Navy questionnaire, that was aimed to discern what sort of facilities the University had in case they were needed in the event of a national emergency. NYU, in effect, took an inventory of its facilities, and its staff.
The 1950 school year saw contracts for some 150 sponsored research projects, with an estimated cost of research at about 3 million dollars. Of this research, the major emphasis was placed upon projects relevant to military needs.
Harold Oliver Voorhis (1896-1985) served as the first Secretary of New York University. Born on July 29, 1896 in Kokomo, Indiana, Voorhis received his B.S. Degree from Colgate University in 1919. In 1920 he studied at Columbia University Law School and in 1922 earned an M.A. degree in Economics from New York University. In 1945 he was awarded an honorary LL.D from Colgate University.
From 1914 to 1915 Voorhis worked as a surveyor's assistant in Saskatchewan Canada. From 1916 to 1919 he acted as the secretary to the President of Colgate University and as secretary to the Chautauqua Institution in 1919. In 1920 Voorhis moved to New York City and took a position as secretary to the Vice President of the National Bank of Commerce. Voorhis began his administrative career at New York University as executive secretary to Chancellor Elmer Ellsworth Brown. Voorhis also taught economics at NYU during this time period.
During Voorhis' tenure the Secretary served as the Chancellor's principal assistant. Under the leadership of five presidents, Elmer Ellsworth Brown (1911-1933), Harry Woodburn Chase (1933-51), James Loomis Madden (acting Chancellor from 1951-1952), Henry Townley Heald (1952-1956), Carroll Vincent Newsom (1956-1962), and James McNaughton Hester (1962-1975).
New York University grew tremendously during this time period and the scope of responsibilities of the office of the Secretary reflected this growth. In 1945 Voorhis became the Vice Chancellor and Secretary under Chancellor Harry Woodburn Chase. In 1955 he was named Vice President and Secretary during Henry T. Heald's presidency. Over time the office supervised a wide array of functions including the administration of: Clerk of the Council/Trustees; Secretary of the Senate; Public Ceremonies; Annual; Commence; Bureau of Public Information; Student Services; Housing; Student Activities Office; University Publicity and Advertising Accreditation Regulation; University Directory; Annual Bibliography; Faculty Handbook, Public Occasions Hall of Fame; University Medal; Seal; Charter Oaths of Allegiance; Scholarship Resources; New York University Press; ROTC and the New York University Art Collection.
Voorhis retired in 1962 after 42 years of service to New York University.
Sources:
"Voorhis Retires," Washington Square Journal, December 1961, Vol. 7, No. 35.
Still, Bayrd, "Evolution of Organization of General Administrative Offices, 1880-1978," (1978). New York University Archives.
New York University, "Self-Study-Final Report." New York: New York University Press, 1956.
Annual Reports of the Vice President and Secretary, 1951-1967. New York University Archives.
Charters and By-Laws of Mew York University, 1925, 1928, 1937, 1951, 1956, 1958, 1960, 1968. New York University Archives.
Newsom, Carroll, "Speech in Honor of H. O. Voorhis," December 12, 1961. Bureau of Public Occasions Records (RG 4.2). New York University Archives.
Office of the President. Records, 1951-196 5 (RG 3.0.6). New York University Archives.
Reports of the Chancellor, 1944-1948. New York University Archives.
Scope and Content Note
The records of the Office of Vice President and Secretary, 1925-1963, reflect Harold Oliver Voorhis' tenure as Secretary (1925-1945), Vice Chancellor and Secretary (1945-1956), and Vice President and Secretary (1956-1962). The materials consist of correspondence, memoranda, committee minutes, reports, printed material, charts, blueprints, petitions, press releases, speeches and photographs. The records reflect the growth, diversity, and complexity of New York University, the development of higher education as a whole, and the reactions and adjustments of a major, private urban university to the changing social concerns during these several decades. They provide information concerning New York University's response to the Depression, World War II and the post-war years, the McCarthy Era, student activism, and many other social, political, economic, and academic issues. Correspondents include: Philip Badger, James Gordon Bennett, Elmer Ellsworth Brown, Marshall Stewart Brown, Harry Woodburn Chase, Walter Wheeler Cook, Frank L. Howley, Theodore Francis Jones, LeRoy Elwood Kimball, Otto Nathan, William Francklyn Paris, Rufus Daniel Smith, and Leslie Jay Tompkins.
Series I: Administrative Correspondence and Subject Files
The administrative correspondence and subject files of the Office of Vice President and Secretary are arranged in one alphabetical subject series filed according to name or primary subject heading. The bulk of the records consist of letters written by Voorhis or a member of his staff on behalf of the Chancellor or President. The administrative functions and offices documented in these files include; Alumni Relations; Councils and Committees; Faculty; Schools/ Colleges and Divisions; Student Affairs and Activities; Physical Facilities; World War II and Post-War Activities; Individuals and Non-University Organizations.
Of particular interest are files relating to Otto Nathan, an instructor of Economics Nathan was a Jewish refugee scholar who fled Germany with the rise of Nazism. Friend and confidant of Albert Einstein, Nathan was suspected of being a Communist Files on Thomas Wolfe who served as an instructor in English in Washington Square College, 1924-1930. Materials in this series also document "Racial and Religious Statistics, 1941-1953," containing statistical data relevant to the ethnic and religious composition of the Washington Square campus. The series also contains materials related to the New York City Slum Clearance Project, chaired by Robert Moses. This project provoked considerable opposition from members of the Greenwich Village community.
Series II: Questionnaires and Faculty Statistics
The series contains questionnaires, University and Faculty Statistics and associated correspondence. The Questionnaires range from 1939-1965 inclusive and Faculty Statistics range from 1934-1945 and 1949-1957. Questionnaires were submitted to Secretary Voorhis's office by the Federal and State Governments' Offices of Education and by private firms and other universities for publication. Statistics recorded include: positions of faculty and administration, volumes in the library, gender, the average salaries by department and rank and detailed data on physical plant space usage and facilities.
Series III: Law Center Campaign
The Series contains minutes, reports, financial statements, correspondence, petitions, press releases, speeches, photographs, printed material and memorabilia concerning the Law Center Foundation and Campaign (1944-1951).
Series IV: Medical Center Campaign
This series consists of 2.25 feet of material pertaining to the New York University Bellevue Medical Center Campaign. The bulk of the collection was created during the years 1947-1948.
Series V: Korean War Materials
This series focuses on federal policies on higher education as they related to war readiness, and national defense preparations and documenting federal policies that effected institutions of higher education.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged chronologically.
The files are grouped into 5 series:
I, Administrative Correspondence and Subject Files
II, Questionnaires and Faculty Statistics
III, Law Center Campaign
IV, Medical Center Campaign
V, Korean War Materials
Access Points
Subject Names:
Badger, Philip.; Bennett, James Gordon, 1841-1918.; Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, 1861-1934.; Brown, Marshall Stewart, 1870-1948.; Chase, Harry Woodburn, 1883-1955.; Cook, Walter Wheeler, 1873-1943.; Howley, Frank L 1903-; Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-; Kimball, Leroy Ellwood, 1888-1962.; Nathan, Otto, 1893-; Paris, William Francklyn, 1871-1954.; Smith, Rufus Daniel, 1884-1953.; Tompkins, Leslie J. (Leslie Jay), b. 1867.; Voorhis, Harold O.
Subject Organizations:
United States. Army. Reserve Officers' Training Corps.; Alumni Federation of New York University, Inc.; American Pioneer Trails Association.; Bellevue Hospital Medical College.; College Entrance Examination Board.; Gallery of Living Art.; New York University Press.; New York University --Administration.; New York University --Buildings.; New York University --Faculty.; New York University --Funds and scholarships.; New York University --History --20th century.; New York University --Students.; New York University. Board of Athletic Control.; New York University. Bureau of Public Information.; New York University. Center for Human Relations.; New York University. College of Arts and Science.; New York University. College of Dentistry.; New York University. College of Engineering.; New York University. College of Fine Arts.; New York University. College of Medicine.; New York University. Commission on Graduate Work.; New York University. Committee on Labor Relations.; New York University. Division of Athletics and Physical Training.; New York University. Division of General Education.; New York University. Faculty Club.; New York University. Graduate School of Arts and Sciences.; New York University. Graduate School of Public Administration.; New York University. Hall of Fame for Great Americans.; New York University. Institute of Comparative Law.; New York University. Institute of Fine Arts.; Loeb Student Center.; New York University. Office of the President.; New York University. Office of the Vice President and Secretary.; New York University. School of Commerce, Accounts, and Finance.; New York University. School of Education.; New York University. School of Law.; Sailors' Snug Harbor (Institution).; Town Hall, Inc.; University of the State of New York.; Washington Square College.; Young Men's Christian Association of the City of New York. Intercollegiate Branch.
Subject Topics:
Universities and Colleges--Administration.; Korean War, 1950-1953.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Questionnaires.
Other Names:
Voorhis, Harold O.
Container List
[The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection.]
- Series I: Administrative Correspondence and Subject Files Container List
  - Aa - Az Miscellaneous, 1935-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Abilities Survey, ca.1945 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Admissions, Office of, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Albert Gallatin Associates, 1956; , 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Allenby, Viscount (Field Marshal) reception, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Alumni Federation, 1928-1959 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - Alumni Gymnasium, 1945-1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Alumnus (Publication), 1932 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Association of University Women, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American .Committee for a Free and United Europe, 1945-1946 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Pioneer Trails Association, 1937-1944 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Society of Civil Engineers, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Andrews, John N., 1941-1954 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Annual Report, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Architecture and Allied Arts, School of, 1934-1956 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Armsey, James W. (Asst. to Chancellor for Public Relations), 1952-1956 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Arnsdorf, Henry Gustav (Registrar), 1926-1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Asia Institute, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Association of American Colleges, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Association of American Medical Colleges, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Athletic Scholarship Program and Fees, 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Athletics, Director of, 1926; , 1951 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Athletics and Physical Training, Division of, 1952-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Axworthy, H. Harold (Director, Bureau of Community Service and Research), 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Ba - Bz Miscellaneous, 1926-1961 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Badger, Philip 0. (Professor, School of Commerce), undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Baer, William B. (Dean, University College), 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Barr, Jean B. (Supervisor of Printing), 1926-1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Beekman-Downtown Hospital, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Bellevue School of Nursing, 1942-1958 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bennett, James Gordon: Herald Tribune Clock (Minerva and the Bell Ringers), 1935-1948 (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
  - Bernard, L- L., 1929- (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bernstein, Felix (Professor of Biometrics, German refugee scholar), 1943-1955 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Better America Federation of California, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Bibliography, 1947-1948 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography Procedure, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 3-6)
  - Biblioteca Belgica, 1938 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Board of Athletic Control: Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Board of Athletic Control: Football Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Board of Athletic Control: James Gilloon, Appointment of, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Board of Athletic Control: Special Athletic Survey Committee, 1949-1950 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Board of Control of All University Non-Athletic Activities, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Bossange, E. Raymond (Dean/ School of Architecture and Allied Arts), 1928-1940 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Brazilian Institute, 1958; , 1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Bronner, Finn J. (Professor of Dentistry), 1953 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Brown, Carleton (Professor of English), 1940 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Brown, Elmer Ellsworth (Chancellor of NYU): A Tribute to: Correspondence and Manuscript, 1943-1944 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Brown, Elmer Ellsworth, A Tribute to: Recipient's List, 1944; , 1954 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Brown, Marshall S. (Dean of Faculties), 1927-1933 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Bureau of Public Information, 1930-1945 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Bureau of Public Occasions, 1954; , undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ca - Cz Miscellaneous, 1929-1957; , undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Campus Stores, 1951-1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Carnegie Corporation, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Centennial Celebration, Committee on, 1928-1931 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Center for Human Relations, 1949-1955 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Center for International Affairs and, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Development, undated (Box 4)
  - Chase, Harry Woodburn (Chancellor): Correspondence, 1935-1957 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
  - Chase, Harry Woodburn (Chancellor): Biographical Material, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chase, Harry Woodburn (Chancellor): Committee on Nomination to Succeed, 1950-1951 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chase, Harry Woodburn (Chancellor): Testimonial Dinner, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Clinical Psychology, Graduate Program, College Entrance Examination Board:, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - General Correspondence, 1947-1948 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - College Entrance Examination Board: Minutes, 1946-1952 (Box 4, Folder 1-3)
  - Commerce, Accounts, and Finance, School of, 1940-1955 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Commission on Graduate Work, 1928-Jun-36 (Box 5, Folder 5-9)
  - Commission on Graduate Work, Oct 1936-1955 (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
  - Commission on Graduate Work: Certificates, 1949-1954 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Committee on Plans and Operations at Washington Square, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Committee on Research, 1928-1929 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Committee on University Commons at Washington Square, 1948-1951 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Committee on University Publications, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Communication Arts Group, 1954-1956 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Communications, School of: Proposal for, 1946 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Community Lecture Service, 1939-1940 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Cook, Walter W.S. (Director, Institute of Fine Arts), 1927-1956 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Cooperative For American Remittances to Europe, -Inc. (C.A.R.E. ), 1946 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Cossart, Mollie, 1947; , 1957 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Coudenhove - Kalergi, Count Richard N., 1947-1948 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Council for Aid to the Visually Handicapped, 1956; , 1957 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Creative Arts Center, Plans of, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Da - Dz Miscellaneous, 1927-1951 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Dean of Women, 1926-1927; , 1950 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Deans, Report of the, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Dentistry, College of, 1927-1957 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Denistry, College of: Deanship: American Dental Association, 1945 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - Denistry, College of: Deanship: General Correspondence, 1944-1946 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Denistry, College of: Deanship: General Correspondence regarding Prospects, 1944-1945 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Dentistry/ College of: Deanship (cont.): General Correspondence regarding Prospects, 1946 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Dentistry/ College of: Deanship: Suggestions for Deanships, 1942; , 1944-1946 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Dentistry/ College of: Deanship: Wright, Walter H., 1942-1943; , 1946 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Dentistry, College of: Religious and Racial Issue, 1945 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Discrimination: Allied discrimination in colleges and universities, 1945-1946 (Box 8, Folder 5)